Guide to the George Aust Papers
Aust (George) Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
George Aust papers
1746 1837
1762 1827
OSB MSS 270
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.5 Linear Feet
(10 boxes)
Aust, George, 1741-1829
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Arthur Freeman on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund, 2002.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Professional Papers, 1763-1827. II. Personal Papers, 1746-1837. III. Correspondence and Other Papers, 1762-1815. IV. Collection Inventories, undated.
George Aust (1741-1829)
George Aust was an English civil servant in the office of the Secretary of State in Great Britain during the reign of King George III. He was born in 1741 near Bath, England. After moving to London, he began his government career in 1763 as a clerk for the Northern Department of the Secretary of State, which would be reorganized as the Foreign Office in 1782. Aust was promoted to senior clerk in 1780 and appointed deputy writer of the official government journal London Gazette by 1781. In 1790, he was appointed Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, a position shared with Sir James Bland Burges, where Aust's responsibilities included the fiscal administration of the Secret Service under Lord William Wyndham Grenville, then Foreign Secretary. Upon retirement in 1796, Aust was appointed Commissary General of Musters and Secretary to the Trustees of Royal Hospital Chelsea, and later served as Secretary to the Westminster Hospital until 1826.
Aust was married three times and remained childless. Little is known about his first wife, who died in 1803. In November 1803, Aust married Sarah Murray (1744-1811), a topographical writer who published two travel books about Scotland. Sarah was previously married to William Murray, son of the third Earl of Dunmore, from 1783 until his death in 1786. Aust subsequently married Catherine Feaver in 1813. He lived in the West End and Chelsea districts of London, where he died in 1829.
Associated Materials
George Aust papers concerning the Secret Service, 1794-1800 (OSB MSS 148). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
Scope and Contents
The George Aust Papers consists of professional papers, legal and financial records, professional and personal correspondence, and other documents pertaining to the life and work of British civil servant George Aust. Aust's papers document his career of over fifty years in government service, including his position as Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs from 1790 to 1796. Correspondents include his wife Sarah Murray Aust; William Eden, first Baron Auckland; Sir James Bland Burges; Thomas Bowdler; Lord William Wyndam Grenville; William Augustus Miles; Lady Barbara Montagu; John Osborn; Bishop Thomas Percy; Sarah Scott; and Philip Yorke, second Earl of Hardwicke. The collection spans the years 1746-1837, with the bulk of the material dating from 1762-1827.
Civil service Great Britain; Diplomacy; Government employees, English; Great Britain History George III, 1760-1820; Great Britain Officials and employees; Great Britain Politics and government 1760-1820; Account books; Account books Great Britain 19th century; Business records; Probate records; Receipts (financial records); Wills; Government employees Great Britain; Auckland, William Eden, Baron, 1744-1814; Aust, George, 1741-1829; Bowdler, Thomas, 1754-1825; Burges, James Bland, Sir, 1752-1824; Grenville, William Wyndham Grenville, Baron, 1759-1834; Hardwicke, Philip Yorke, Earl of, 1720-1790; Miles, William Augustus, 1753?-1817; Montagu, Barbara, -1765; Murray, Sarah, 1744-1811; Osborn, John, 1743-1814; Percy, Thomas, 1729-1811; Scott, Sarah, 1720-1795; Great Britain. Foreign Office Officials and employees; Royal Hospital (Chelsea, London, England); Westminster Hospital
- Professional Papers, 1763 1827; 1; 2.5 Linear Feet; (3 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Professional Papers consists of documents related to Aust's civil service career in the Secretary of State for the Northern Department (which became the Foreign Office in 1782) from 1763 to 1796, particularly his appointment as Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, as well as later positions at the Commissary General of Musters office, Royal Hospital Chelsea, and the Westminster Hospital. Files include official documents, drafts, memoranda, lists, administrative records, financial records, salary negotiations, and professional correspondence concerning diplomatic work, foreign affairs, politics, the military, and veteran's pensions. Correspondents include diplomats, statesmen, and other government officials, such as Lord William Wyndham Grenville, then Foreign Secretary; Sir James Bland Burges; and William Eden, first Baron Auckland.
  "The diamond snuffbox affair," as documented in the collection inventory in Series IV, refers to an incident during Aust's tenure as Under-Secretary of State, wherein fellow Under-Secretary Sir James Bland Burges received a cash gift and diamond-studded snuffbox in an exchange of diplomatic gifts with Russia, while Aust received nothing.
  Arrangement
  Arranged in chronological order, with files grouped by office held. Correspondence is filed at the end of the sequence.
  - Secretary of State for the Northern Department and Foreign Office
    - "Titles of Foreign Princes as addressed by His Majesty," and "Forms of the Address and Superscription used by His Majesty in his Cachette Letters to the several Crowned Heads and Princes of Europe", 1763 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "A Bishop's Oath of Allegiance," draft, [1779?] (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 108)
    - Letters from William Eden, first Baron Auckland, with letters from Francis Freeling, Lord Grenville, Viscount Bute, and Sir James Marriott, 1791 1800 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - "The diamond snuffbox affair," concerning gifts from Catherine the Great to English diplomats, with letters from Sir James Bland Burges, and Louis Dutens, 1795 1796 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Commissary General of Musters office, 1796 1827 (Box 1, Folder 4-9)
  - Commissary General of Musters office, 1805 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 107)
  - Commissary General of Musters, on account of fees and contingencies of the said office, 1812 1818 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Royal Hospital Chelsea, 1808 1814 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Royal Hospital Chelsea, 1807 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 109)
  - Royal Hospital Chelsea, supplications by or on behalf of military men, 1795 1826 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - The Westminster Hospital, 1823 1826 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Salary negotiations with the War Department, with letters from Lord Palmerston and Nicholas Vansittart, 1812 1822 (Box 2, Folder 17-19)
  - Correspondence
    - Letter from Morton Eden, first Baron Henley, 1793-06-15 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Letter from Sir Richard Clayton, 1797-11-10 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Letter from John Waliot, with mention of Napoleon Bonaparte, 1802-02-21 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Letter from George Aust to George Canning, 1804-11-08 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Letters from Robert Jocelyn, Earl of Roden, and John Dalrymple, sixth Earl of Stair, 1805-09-25 1805-11-01 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Letter from Sir Robert Liston, 1811-03-06 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Letters from Edward Stanley, and family, 1815 1816 (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
- Personal Papers, 1746 1837; 2; 1.25 Linear Feet; (3 boxes)
  Personal Papers consists of records concerning Aust's roles as trustee and executor, personal financial records, and charity subscriptions. Materials include wills and related legal documents, account books, household expenses, subscriptions for newspapers and journals, bills, and receipts. The series also includes personal correspondence, and a small selection of Aust's literary writings.
  Arranged by subject, reflecting the order found at time of acquisition.
  - Estates, trusts, and wills
    - Hammond, Ann Francis, 1802 1827 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Rolleston, G.W., 1802 1826 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Woodford, Sir Ralph, and family, 1808 1812 (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
    - Woodford, Sir Ralph, and family, 1778 1812 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 110)
  - Personal financial records
    - Account book, 1787 1794 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Account book, 1793 1802 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Account book, 1795 1802 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Account book, 1812 1818 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Account book, 1818 1822 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Account with Thomas Hammond, 1799 1801 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Account with Thomas Lockington, 1801 1804 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Business with Thrupp and Son, 1812 1817 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Business with Thrupp and Son, 1811 1819 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 111)
    - Debt booklet, "W. Fraser", 1789 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Finance booklet, 1815 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Mortgage with Cooper Crawford, undated (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 112)
    - Newspaper account book, 1765 1774 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Receipts, 1814–1827, undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Unsorted accounting, 1785–1824, undated (Box 4, Folder 45-46)
    - Unsorted correspondence, bills, and receipts, 1746 1837 (Box 4, Folder 47-52)
    - Unsorted correspondence, bills, and receipts, 1775 1837 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 113)
    - Unsorted correspondence, bills, and receipts, vellum, 1808 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 114)
  - Charities, 1801 1827 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Charities, 1801 1827 (Box 5, Folder 54-55)
  - Letters from Robertson, William Philip Colyear, 1806 1816 (Box 5, Folder 56-57)
  - Letter from Brooke, Samuel, 1824-12-09 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Letter from "Miss Dee" on behalf of Maria, Duchess of Gloucester, 1807-07-08 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Prospectus by Butler, Reverend Weedon, circa 1790 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Lists of visitors to Staffa and Iona, circa 1808 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Autograph manuscript verses for the birthday of Francis Osborne, fifth Duke of Leeds, circa 1797 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Schedule to two houses, no. 7 and 8, Paradise Row, Chelsea, 1805-03-15 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Unsorted personal correspondence, 1796 1827 (Box 5, Folder 64-65a)
- Correspondence and Other Papers, 1762 1815; 3; 3.75 Linear Feet; (4 boxes)
  This series contains correspondence and personal and professional papers of Sarah Murray Aust, George Aust's second wife, and others. Most of the correspondence is addressed to George Aust. Sarah Aust's papers consist of personal letters, financial records, legal records concerning her first husband William Murray, as well as drafts, publishing correspondence, and accounts with printers and booksellers related to her travel writing.
  The series also contains letters from diplomat John Osborn, and a related collection of "Osborniana," including letters to Aust from Osborn's brother, Sir George Osborn, and Osborn's wills and estate documents. Additional correspondents are philanthropist and literary editor Thomas Bowdler; writers William Augustus Miles and Bishop Thomas Percy; philanthropist Lady Barbara Montagu; novelist Sarah Scott; and statesman Philip Yorke, second Earl of Hardwicke.
  Arranged alphabetically by last name.
  - Aust, Sarah Murray
    - General papers, 1799 1812 (Box 5, Folder 66-68)
    - General papers, 1811 1812 (Box 9 (Oversize), Folder 115)
    - Account book, executorship of William Murray's estate, 1786 1811 (Box 6, Folder 69)
    - Account book, 1804 1811 (Box 6, Folder 70)
    - Account book, 1809 (Box 6, Folder 71)
    - Account book, 1810 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Notes on minerals, autograph manuscript, undated (Box 6, Folder 73)
    - Probate of the Will of the Honorable William Murray, 1787 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 116)
    - Release of sums appointed by the will of the late Mrs. Aust, 1812-01-29 (Box 10 (Oversize), Folder 117)
    - "A short descriptive arrangement of Gems, stones and spars, Earths metals and semi metals," autograph manuscript, undated (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - Bowdler, Thomas, 1810 1811 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Miles, William Augustus, 1776 1808 (Box 7, Folder 76-77)
  - Montagu, Lady Barbara, 1762, 1764 (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - Osborn, John, 1799 1814 (Box 7, Folder 79-82)
  - Osborniana
    - Letters from Sir George Osborn, and Count Semyon Vorontsov [Woronzow], regarding the prisoner-of-war affair, 1803 (Box 7, Folder 83)
    - Letters from Sir George Osborn, regarding message from John Osborn relating to Catherine the Great, 1809-07 (Box 7, Folder 84)
    - Letters from John Miliquet, 1807 1809 (Box 7, Folder 85)
    - Letters from Heneage Osborn, Thomas Metcalfe, and Mr. Luntly, financial agent, regarding Luntly's frauds, 1810 1811 (Box 7, Folder 86-87)
    - Letters from Sir George Osborn and other correspondents, regarding Patent Customers at Custom House, Cardiff, 1812 1813 (Box 7, Folder 88-90)
    - Draft will, Additional Codicils, and Minutes of the Will and Codicils of John Osborn Esquire, 1810 1814 (Box 7, Folder 91)
    - Executorship of estate, 1814 1815 (Box 7, Folder 92)
    - Unsorted correspondence and documents, 1802 1815 (Box 8, Folder 93-94)
  - Percy, Bishop Thomas
    - Autograph letters, signed (#1–9), 1800 1804 (Box 8, Folder 95)
    - Dictated letters, signed (#10–31), 1804 1811 (Box 8, Folder 96-98)
    - Insertions and associated material (#32–44), 1801 1811 (Box 8, Folder 99-100)
  - Scott, Sarah, circa 1760s–1790s (Box 8, Folder 101-104)
  - Yorke, Philip, second Earl of Hardwicke, 1778 1787 (Box 8, Folder 105)
- Collection Inventories, undated; 4
  Two inventories prepared for the Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library contain detailed descriptions of the collection's materials, providing historical context and biographical information about Aust and his correspondents.
  - Inventories, undated (Box 8, Folder 106)